# John A. Ramey II, Ph.D.

Data Scientist, BlackLocus Austin, Texas, USA johnramey@gmail.com http://ramhiser.com

#### **Personal Statement**

I build intelligent systems that utilize data to inform human users to make better decisions and to automate processes that require extensive time, labor, and resources. My research interests are in statistical and machine learning with an emphasis on Bayesian methods.

### **Education**

Baylor University	Waco, TX
Ph.D. Statistics	$July \ 2012$
- Adviser: Dean M. Young, Ph.D.	
Baylor University	Waco, TX
M.Sc. Statistics	Dec. 2009
Baylor University	Waco, TX
B.Sc. Mathematics (Minor: Computer Science)	Aug. 2008

### **Publications**

Finak, G., Frelinger J., Jiang, W., Newell, E., **Ramey, J.**, Davis, M., Kalams, S., de Rosa, S., and Gottardo, R. (2014) "OpenCyto: An Open Source Infrastructure for Scalable, Robust, Reproducible, and Automated, End-to-End Flow Cytometry Data Analysis," *PLOS Computational Biology*, 10, 8.

Ramey, J. A. and Young, P. D. (2013) "A Comparison of Regularization Methods Applied to the Linear Discriminant Function with High-Dimensional Microarray Data," *Journal of Statistical Computation and Simulation*, 83, 3, 581–596.

McDermott, J., Wang, J., Mitchell, H., Webb-Robertson, B., Hafen, R., Ramey, J., and Rodland, K. (2013) "Challenges in Biomarker Discovery: Combining Expert Insights with Statistical Analysis of Complex Omics Data," *Expert Opinion on Medical Diagnostics*, 7, 1, 37–51.

## **Articles Submitted for Publication**

Sego, L. H., Shulman, S. A., Anderson, K. K., **Ramey, J. A.**, Wilson, J. E., Pulsipher, B. A., and Sieber, W. K. "A Bayesian Acceptance Sampling Model for Combining Judgmental and Randomly Selected Samples." (under revision)

## Awards, Grants & Honors

Travel Grant, \$1,000 – Baylor University	2011
Outstanding Graduate Student – Department of Statistical Science, Baylor University	2011
JSM Stat Bowl – Champion	2010
Outstanding First Year Graduate Student – Department of Statistical Science	2009
Baylor University Dean's Scholarship	008-2012

## Research Experience

Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center

Postdoctoral Research Fellow

August 2012-October 2013

Pacific Northwest National Laboratory

Richland, WA

Research Associate, National Security Internship Program

June 2011 - July 2012

Statistical and Machine Learning Research Group

Department of Statistical Science, Baylor University

Seattle, WA

August 2012-October 2013

Waco, TX

2009-2012

Research Experience for Undergraduates at The Ohio State University Columbus, OH Vertical Integration of Research and Education in Computational Mathematics Summer 2004

#### Journal Reviewer

Journal of Statistical Computation and Simulation

Journal of Statistical Software

## **Conference Papers**

Ramey, J. A. and Young, D. M. (2010). A More Computationally Efficient Model Selection Method for Regularized Discriminant Analysis, Joint Statistical Meetings Proceedings, Vancouver, BC, Canada.

### **Invited Talks**

- Ramey, J. A. (November 2012). Automated Bayesian Gating with OpenCyto. FlowCAP-III Summit, National Institute of Health, Bethesda, Maryland, USA.
- Ramey, J. A. (February 2012). Diagonal Discriminant Analysis with Simultaneous Diagonalization of Covariance Matrices. Fred Hutchison Cancer Research Center, Seattle, Washington, USA.
- Ramey, J. A. (February 2011). Diagonal Discriminant Analysis after Simultaneous Diagonalization of Covariance Matrices with High-Dimensional Data. Pacific Northwest National Laboratory, Richland, Washington, USA.

#### **Presentations**

Ramey, J., Stein, C. K., and Young, D. M. (June 2013) *High-Dimensional Regularized Discriminant Analysis*. Southern Regional Council on Statistics 2013, Louisville, Kentucky, USA. (poster)

Ramey, J., Finak, G., Jiang, M., Taghiyar, J., de Rosa, S., Brinkman, R., and Gottardo, R. (May 2013) Automated Flow Cytometry Data Analysis with the OpenCyto Framework. Cyto 2013, San Diego, California, USA. (poster)

Ramey, J. A. (August 2012). On the Estimation of Similarity Indices in Clustering Evaluation. Joint Statistical Meetings, San Diego, California, USA.

Ramey, J. A. and Young, D. M. (August 2010). Efficient Model Selection for Regularized Discriminant Analysis. Joint Statistical Meetings, Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada. (poster)

Ramey, J. A. (April 2010). Bayesian Regularized Logistic Regression in High-Dimensional Classification. Instituto Panamericano de Estudios Avanzados en Probabilidad y Estadística: Semana en Métodos de Reducción de Dimensión. Centro de Investigación en Matemáticas, A.C. Guanajuato, Mexico. (poster)

#### **Professional Service**

Session on Generalized Linear and Mixed Models
Chair

Joint Statistical Meetings August 2012, San Diego, CA, USA

## **Teaching Experience**

#### Elementary Statistics

Teacher of Record

Baylor University Aug. 2009 - May 2011

- Taught this freshman level course in the Statistics Department.
- Developed homework, quizzes and exams for the class.
- Attended weekly meetings to enhance and improve teaching skills and techniques.

### Statistics Department Tutoring Lab

Baylor University

Graduate Teaching Assistant

Aug. 2008 - May 2011

- Conducted one-on-one and group tutoring to students in undergraduate statistics courses.

#### Statistics for Psychology Majors

Baylor University

Graduate Teaching Assistant

Aug. 2008 - Jul. 2009

- Provided weekly supplemental instruction to a small group of undergraduate students.
- Lectured to a large number of students in an auditorium during professor absences.
- Led weekly course seminars.

# Software Projects (Available at http://github.com/ramey)

activelearning: An R Package for Querying Unlabeled Observations with Active Learning.

clusteval: Evaluation of Clustering Algorithms in R.

datamicroarray: Collection of High-Dimensional Microarray Data Sets.

errorest: An R Package for Error Rate Estimation for Statistical and Machine Learning.

openCyto: An R Package for Automated Analysis of Flow Cytometry Data.

sparsediscrim: An R Package for Regularized and Sparse Discriminant Analysis Methods.

## **Professional Membership**

American Statistical Association

2008-present

Association for Computing Machinery

2011-present

Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers

2011-present

## Skills

#### Programming and Markup Languages

Skilled: R

- Proficient: BUGS, LATEX, Linux, Python, SQL

- Experienced: ASP, C#, C++, Java, Mathematica, MATLAB, .NET, PHP

#### Miscellaneous

Innovation in Graduate Education Challenge

National Science Foundation 2013

Judge

Fred Hutchinson Cancer Center

Systems and Computational Biology Affinity Group Co-Organizer

2013

**United States Soccer Federation** 

1995 - present Referee

# References

# Dr. Dean Young (Ph.D. Adviser)

Department of Statistical Science, Baylor University

# Dr. John Seaman

Department of Statistical Science, Baylor University

# Dr. Landon Sego

Applied Statistics and Computational Modeling, Pacific Northwest National Laboratory

# Dr. James Stamey

Department of Statistical Science, Baylor University